｢There was a hungry crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢who wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
｢if only this beak were a little longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢that feed would be a bit closer｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢a crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは 考え る ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe, formulate a hypothesis, experiment and consider.
( 斎藤 )観察し 仮 説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Learn the way of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
Today we begin with a Thinking Hint.
今日は ｢考えるﾋﾝﾄ｣から｡
Everyone, how can you think about the next problem?
みなさんは 次の問題を どう考えるでしょうか？
That is to say, these three.
(山本) つまり この３つ｡
Now, question 2.
では 問いの２｡
Suppose there was one bacteria in this cup.
このｺｯﾌﾟの中に あるﾊﾞｸﾃﾘｱが １ 個 いたとします｡
Within one minute, the bacteria divides
このﾊﾞｸﾃﾘｱは １分間に １回 分れつします｡
That is to say, after one minute, there's two bacteria. In two minutes, four.
つまり １分後は２個 ２分後は４個 →
In three minutes, it became eight.
３分後は８個と なっていきます｡
The bacteria continues dividing.
このﾊﾞｸﾃﾘｱが 分れつをくり返し →
In one hour the cup is completely full.
１時間後には ちょうど ｺｯﾌﾟ一ぱいに なりました｡
Now this is the question.
ここで問題です｡
Within the one hour
この１時間の どこかで →
there is a point where the cup is exactly half full.
ｺｯﾌﾟが ちょうど半分になった ﾀｲﾐﾝｸﾞが あるはずです｡
This point where the cup precisely half full
この ちょうど半分になったのは →
how many minutes from the start is it?
最初から計って 何分後の事でしょうか？
Please think now. You have 30 seconds.
では 30秒間 考えてみて下さい｡
It's time.
時間です｡
This bacteria has a property of doubling each minute.
このﾊﾞｸﾃﾘｱは １分ごとに 倍々にふえる 性質 でした｡
You can think about this in the opposite way.
これを 逆か ら考えると →
That each minute before, it continually halves.
１分前は つねに ½ になるという事です｡
That is to say when the cup is exactly half full
つまり ｺｯﾌﾟに ちょうど半分だったのは →
Is one minute before 60 minutes. 59 minutes after the start time.
60分の １分前 59分後｡
We can think in reverse.
逆から考える｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Now, today our problem deals with water and some scales.
( 蒼井 )さて 今日は 水と てんびんを使った問題です｡
Please look at these scales.
この てんびんを見て下さい｡
We place a filled beaker on them.
水の入った ﾋﾞｰｶｰが のっていますね｡
It's balanced.
おもりとの つりあいが とれています｡
Now, i stand like this right near the scales.
今 私は てんびんのわきに このように立っています｡
I raise my hand and, without touching the beaker...
その私が 手をのばして このﾋﾞｰｶｰに ふれずに →
gently put my finger in the water. What will happen to the scales?
指を そっと水の中に入れると てんびんは どうなるでしょうか？
Well, let's give it a try.
では やってみましょう｡
We'll reveal the answer at the end of the program.
答えは 番組の最後に 発表します｡
Think really carefully, won't you?
よ～く考えておいて下さいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
And now the answer to our problem.
では 先ほどの答えです｡
Did everyone think carefully?
みなさん ちゃんと考えましたか？
Well then, let's try it.
では やってみましょう｡
Let's go. Please look very carefully.
いきますよ｡ よ～く見ておいて下さいね｡
When I put the tip of my finger in, the scales shifted.
指先を入れると かたむきました｡
Why do you think that is, even though I only put my finger in the water?
水の中に 指を入れてるだけなのに どうしてでしょう？
When I put my finger into the water...
水の中に 指を入れると →
That part of my finger displaces some water.
その指の分だけ 水を おしのけます｡
Really, this...
実は それが…｡
From here on we think for ourselves.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here on we're all thinking crows.
これからは みんなが考えるｶﾗｽ｡